What I'm going to do is to just give a few notes,
ما سأفعله الآن هو إعطاء بعض الملاحظات
and this is from a book I'm preparing called
و هي من كتاب أعده حاليا اسمه:
"Letters to a Young Scientist."
"رسائل إلى العالم الشاب"
I'd thought it'd be appropriate to
و رأيت أنه من المناسب
present it, on the basis that I have had extensive experience
أن أعرضه على أساس أنه لدي خبرة واسعة
in teaching, counseling scientists across a broad array of fields.
في تدريس و إرشاد العلماء عبر مجموعة واسعة من المجالات
And you might like to hear some of the principles that I've developed in doing
و ربما تحبون أن تستمعوا إلى بعض المبادئ التي قمت على تطويرها في
that teaching and counseling.
عملية التعليم و الإرشاد
So let me begin by urging you,
لذا دعوني أبدا بحثكم
particularly you on the youngsters' side,
و خصوصا على الجانب الشاب منكم
on this path you've chosen,
على هذا الطريق الذي اخترتم
to go as far as you can.
لتذهبوا إلى أبعد ما يمكن
The world needs you, badly.
لأن العالم بأمس الحاجة إليكم
Humanity is now fully into the techno-scientific age.
إن الإنسانية الآن هي بالكامل بعصر التكنولوجيا و العلم
There is going to be no turning back.
و هي بنقطة اللاعودة
Although varying among disciplines -- say, astrophysics,
على الرغم من تعدد المجالات, الفيزياء الفلكية على سبيل المثال
molecular genetics, the immunology, the microbiology, the public
أو علم الوراثة أو المناعة او علم الأحياء المجهرية أو الصحة العامة
health, to the new area of the human body as a symbiont,
إلى علوم جسم الإنسان
to public health, environmental science.
إلى الصحة العامة و علوم البيئة
Knowledge in medical science and science overall
إن العلم في مجال الصحة و العلوم عامة
is doubling every 15 to 20 years.
يتضاعف كل 15-20 عاماً
Technology is increasing at a comparable rate.
و التكنولوجيا تزداد بنفس النسبة
Between them, the two already pervade,
وما بينهما قد انتشر
as most of you here seated realize,
كما يدرك معظم الحاضرين هنا
every dimension of human life.
كل بعد من أبعاد حياة الإنسان.
So swift is the velocity of the techno-scientific revolution,
لذا فسريعة جدا هي ثورة العلم و التكنولوجيا،
so startling in its countless twists and turns, that no one can predict
بدء من العدد اللانهائي من الاتجاهات التي لا يمكن لأحد أن يتوقعها
its outcome even a decade from the present moment.
نتائجها التي تظهر بعد عقد من الزمن من الآن.
There will come a time, of course,
بالطبع, سيأتي اليوم،
when the exponential growth of discovery and knowledge,
حين نرى النمو الأسي للاكتشاف و المعرفة،
which actually began in the 1600s,
الذي بدأ في الواقع منذ القرن السابع عشر،
has to peak and level off,
سيصل إلى قمة نشاطه و يستقر،
but that's not going to matter to you.
و لكن هذا لن يؤثر عليكم.
The revolution is going to continue
لأن الثورة سوف تستمر
for at least several more decades.
لعقود عديدة على الأقل.
It'll render the human condition
سوف تجعل حالة الإنسان
radically different from what it is today.
مختلفة بشكل جذري عما هي عليه الآن.
Traditional fields of study are going to continue to grow
سوف تستمر المجالات التقليدية للبحوث بالتطور
and in so doing, inevitably they will meet and create new disciplines.
و حتما سوف يكتشفون مجالات جديدة.
In time, all of science will come to be
آنذاك، سوف تصبح كل العلوم
a continuum of description, an explanation of networks, of principles and laws.
استمرارية للوصف وشرحاً لشبكات المبادئ والقوانين..
That's why you need not just be training
لهذا لا تحتاجون فقط للتدريب
in one specialty, but also acquire breadth in other fields,
في تخصص واحد فقط بل اكتسبوا كذلك نطاقا واسعا في مجالات أخرى،
related to and even distant from your own initial choice.
لها علاقة قريبة أو بعيدة بما اخترتموه في البداية.
Keep your eyes lifted and your head turning.
أبقوا اعينكم مفتوحة و أنظروا من حولكم.
The search for knowledge is in our genes.
البحث و المعرفة موجود في مورثاتنا.
It was put there by our distant ancestors
لقد تم توارثها من أسلافنا الأوائل
who spread across the world,
الذين انتشروا في أرجاء العالم،
and it's never going to be quenched.
و لن تطفأ أبدا.
To understand and use it sanely,
لذا، حتى نفهمها ونستخدمها بعقلانية،
as a part of the civilization yet to evolve
كجزء من الحضارة التي تحتلج للتطور
requires a vastly larger population of scientifically trained people like you.
نحتاج إلى عدد كبير من الأشخاص المدربين علميا مثلكم.
In education, medicine, law, diplomacy,
في العلم و الصحة و القانون و الدبلوماسية
government, business and the media that exist today.
و الحكومة و المال و الإعلام المتواجد في أيامنا هذه.
Our political leaders need at least a modest degree of scientific
قادتنا السياسيون يلزمهم على الأقل درجة متواضعة في المعرفة
literacy, which most badly lack today --
العلمية، والتي يفتقر إليها معظمهم اليوم --
no applause, please.
لا تصفقوا، رجاءً.
It will be better for all
سيكون ذلك أفضل للجميع
if they prepare before entering office rather than learning on the job.
إذا تجهزوا لمهمتهم قبل أن يباشروا العمل بها بدل أن يتعلموها بعد توليهم منصبهم
Therefore you will do well to act on the side,
لذلك ستبلون جيدا إن اشتغلتم بالموازاة،
no matter how far into the laboratory
مهما خضتم في العمل بالمختبرات
you may go, to serve as teachers
قد تذهبون، لتخدموا كالمعلمين
during the span of your career.
خلال فترة حياتكم المهنية.
I'll now proceed quickly,
سوف أنتقل الآن بسرعة،
and before else, to a subject that is both a vital asset
و قبل أي شيء إلى الموضوع الذي هو في نفس الوقت أصل حيوي
and a potential barrier to a scientific career.
وعائق محتمل للمهنة العلمية.
If you are a bit short in mathematical skills,
إذا كنت ضعيفا بعض الشيء في المهارات الرياضية،
don't worry.
لا تقلق.
Many of the most successful scientists
العديد من العلماء
at work today are mathematically semi-literate.
الذي يعملون حاليا يفتقرون إلى المهارة العالية في الرياضيات
A metaphor will serve here:
و التشبيه سيفيد هنا :
Where elite mathematicians and statisticians
في حين أن نخبة الرياضياتيين والإحصائيين
and theorists often serve as architects in the expanding realm
والمنظرّين، غالبا ما يعملون كمعماريين في حقل شرح
of science, the remaining large majority of
العلوم، والغالبية العظمى المتبقية من
basic applied scientists, including a large portion of those who could be
العلماء التطبيقيين الأساسيين، وضمنهم جزء كبيرا من الذين يمكن
said to be of the first rank, are the ones who map the terrain, they scout
القول أنهم في المرتبة الأولى، هم الذين يرسمون الخريطة، ويكتشفون
the frontiers, they cut the pathways,
الحدود ويقطعون المسارات،
they raise the buildings along the way.
و ينشؤون المباني على امتداد الطريق.
Some may have considered me foolhardy,
بعضكم يظن بأنني متهور،
but it's been my habit to brush aside the fear of mathematics
لكن باتت من عاداتي أن أتجنب خوفي من الرياضيات
when talking to candidate scientists.
عندما أتكلم مع العلماء المرشحين.
During 41 years of teaching biology at Harvard,
خلال 41 عاما من تدريس علم الأحياء في جامعة هارفرد،
I watched sadly as bright students turned away
رأيت بحزن الطلاب العباقرة يُبعَدون
from the possibility of a scientific career
عن مهنة علمية محتملة
or even from taking non-required courses in science
أو حتى أخذ المواد الإختيارية في العلوم
because they were afraid of failure.
لأنهم كانوا يخافون من الفشل.
These math-phobes deprive science and medicine
هذا الخوف من الرياضيات يحرم العلوم والصحة
of immeasurable amounts of badly needed talent.
من عدد لا يحصى من المواهب التي نحتاجها بيأس.
Here's how to relax your anxieties, if you have them:
سأتلو بعض النصائح للتغلب على المخاوف في حال وجودها:
Understand that mathematics is a language
افهم أن الرياضيات هي لغة
ruled like other verbal languages,
تتبع نفس قوانين اللغات الشفهية،
or like verbal language generally, by its own grammar
أو أنها كلغة شفهية بقواعدها النحوية الخاصة
and system of logic.
ونظامها المنطقي.
Any person with average quantitative intelligence
أي شخص بمستوى ذكاء كمي عادي
who learns to read and write mathematics
ممن يتعلم كيف يقرأ و يكتب الرياضيات
at an elementary level will, as in verbal language, have little difficulty
في مرحلة أساسية سيتعلمها، كما اللغة المنطوقة، مع بعض الصعوبات
picking up most of the fundamentals
عن طريق فهم معظم الأساسيات
if they choose to master the mathspeak of most disciplines of science.
و إذا اختاروا أن يبرعوا في رياضيات معظم مجالات العلوم.
The longer you wait to become at least semi-literate
كلما انتظرت أكتر لتصبح على الأقل شبه متعلم
the harder the language of mathematics will be to master, just as again in any verbal
سيصبح إتقان لغة الرياضيات أصعب، مثل أي لغة شفهية
language, but it can be done at any age.
لكنها ممكنة في أي سن كان.
I speak as an authority
و أنا أتكلم بصفتي سلطة نفوذ
on that subject, because I'm an extreme case.
في هذا الموضوع، لأنني حالة مستعصية.
I didn't take algebra until my freshman year
لم أدرس الجبر حتى سنتي الأولى بالجامعة
at the University of Alabama.
في جامعة ألاباما.
They didn't teach it before then.
و لم يكونو يدرسونها قبل ذلك.
I finally got around to calculus as a 32-year-old tenured professor at Harvard,
وأخيرا في علم التفاضل والتكامل في سن ال32 كأستاذ مثبت في جامعة هارفرد،
where I sat uncomfortably in classes with undergraduate students,
حيث جلست بشكل غير مريح في فصل مع الطلاب الجامعيين،
little more than half my age.
أكبر بقليل من نصف سني.
A couple of them were students
والبعض منهم كانو طلاب عندي
in a course I was giving on evolutionary biology.
في مادة علم الأحياء التطورية.
I swallowed my pride, and I learned calculus.
تجاوزت كبريائي وتعلمت التفاضل والتكامل.
I found out that in science and all its applications,
لقد اكتشفت أنه في العلوم وكل تطبيقاتها،
what is crucial is not that technical ability,
ما يهم ليس هو القدرة التقنية،
but it is imagination in all of its applications.
بل هو تخيلها بكل تطبيقاتها.
The ability to form concepts with images of entities and processes
القدرة على تشكيل مبادئ من خلال كيانات وعمليات
pictured by intuition.
مصورة عن طريق الحدس.
I found out that advances in science rarely come upstream
لقد وجدت أن التقدم في العلوم نادرا ما ينبع
from an ability to stand at a blackboard
من القدرة على الوقوف أمام السبورة
and conjure images from unfolding mathematical propositions
وإستحضار صور عن طريق كشف مقترحات رياضية
and equations.
ومعادلات.
They are instead the products of downstream imagination leading to hard work,
لكنه وبدل ذلك، نتيجة الخيال المنبثق الذي يقود للعمل المرهق،
during which mathematical reasoning may or may not prove to be relevant.
في الوقت الذي قد يثبت فيه المنطق الرياضي أو لا يثبت كونه ذا صلة.
Ideas emerge when a part of the real or imagined world is studied
تنتج الأفكار عندما يدرس جزء من العالم الواقعي و الخيالي
for its own sake.
لذاته.
Of foremost importance is a thorough, well-organized knowledge
وبأهمية قصوى، فإن معرفة شاملة ومنظمة جيدا
of all that is known of the relevant entities and processes that might be involved in that domain
لكل ما هو معروف عن الكيانات ذات الصلة والعمليات التي قد تكون مشمولة في ذلك المجال
you propose to enter.
الذي تقترح الدخول إليه.
When something new is discovered,
عندما يتم اكتشاف شيء جديد،
it's logical then that one of the follow-up steps is
من المنطقي آنذاك أن واحدة من الخطوات التالية هي
to find the mathematical and statistical methods to move its analysis forward.
إيجاد الطريقة الإحصائية الرياضية لدفع هذا التحليل إلى الأمام.
If that step proves too difficult for
إذا أثبتت هذه الخطوة أنها صعبة جدا لهذا
the person or team that made the discovery,
الشخص أو الفريق المكتشف،
a mathematician can then be added by them
يمكن لهم أن يضموا عالم رياضيات
as a collaborator.
كمتعاون معهم.
Consider the following principle,
فكر بالمبدأ التالي،
which I will modestly call Wilson's Principle Number One:
والذي سأسمية بكل تواضع مبدأ ويلسون الأول:
It is far easier for scientists
إنه من السهل بكثير على العلماء
including medical researchers, to require needed collaboration
بما فيهم الباحثون في الطب، أن يلطلبوا حاجتهم من التعاون
in mathematics and statistics
في الرياضيات والإحصائيات
than it is for mathematicians and statisticians
مما هو عليه بالنسبة لعلماء الرياضيات والإحصاء
to find scientists able to make use of their equations.
في إيجاد علماء يتمكنون من استخدام معادلاتهم.
It is important in choosing the direction to take in science
من المهم في اختيار اتجاه العلم
to find the subject at your level of competence that interests you deeply,
لإيجاد الموضوع على مستواك من الكفاءة الذي يثير اهتمامك بعمق،
and focus on that.
والتركيز على ذلك.
Keep in mind, then, Wilson's Second Principle:
ضع في اعتبارك آنذاك قانون ويلسون الثاني:
For every scientist, whether researcher, technician,
لكل عالم سواء كان باحثا أو تقنيا
teacher, manager or businessman,
معلما أو مديرا أو رجل أعمال،
working at any level of mathematical competence,
يعمل على أي مستوى من الكفاءة في الرياضيات،
there exists a discipline in science or medicine
يوجد تخصص في العلم أو الطب
for which that level is enough to achieve excellence.
يكون فيها ذلك المستوى كافيا لتحقيق الامتياز.
Now I'm going to offer quickly
والآن سوف أعرض عليكم سريعا
several more principles that will be useful
بعض من المبادئ الأخرى التي ستكون مفيدة
in organizing your education and career,
في تنظيم تعليمك وسيرتك المهنية،
or if you're teaching, how you might
أو إذا كنت معلما، كيف يمكنك
enhance your own teaching and counseling of young scientists.
أن تحسن من أسلوبك في التعليم و الإرشاد للعلماء الناشئين.
In selecting a subject in which to conduct original research,
في اختيار الموضوع التي ستجري فيه البحث الأصلي،
or to develop world-class expertise,
أو لتطوير كفاءة على مستوى عالمي،
take a part of the chosen discipline that is sparsely inhabited.
أن تكون جزء من موضوع قليلا ما يختاره أحد.
Judge opportunity by how few other students and researchers
أحكم على الفرصة بقلة عدد الطلاب و الباحثين
are on hand.
الموجودين.
This is not to de-emphasize the essential requirement
هذا ليس تقليلا من أهمية المطلوب الرئيسي
of broad training, or the value of apprenticing yourself
من التدريب واسع المجال، أو من قيمة احترافك الذاتي
in ongoing research to programs of high quality.
في الأبحاث الجارية إلى مستوى عال من الجودة.
It is important also to acquire older mentors within these successful
من المهم أيضاً الحصول على الإرشاد من الأكبر سنأ في هذه
programs, and to make friends and colleagues of your age
البرامج الناجحة، وتكوين صداقات وزمالات من نفس الفئة العمرية
for mutual support.
للحصول على الدعم المتبادل.
But through it all, look for a way to break out,
لكن من خلال هذا كله ابحث عن طريق للخروج،
to find a field and subject not yet popular.
لإيجاد مجال وموضوع ليس مشهورا بعد.
We have seen this demonstrated already in the talks preceding mine.
وقد رأينا هذا الكلام مثبتا في المحادثات التي سبقتني.
There is the quickest way advances are likely to occur,
هناك الطريقة الأسرع التي قد تحصل بها التقدمات غالبا،
as measured in discoveries per investigator per year.
كما تمت قياسها بعدد الإكتشافات لكل باحث في السنة.
You may have heard the
ربما تكونوا قد سمعتم عن
military dictum for the gathering of armies:
القول المأثور لتجميع الجيوش:
March to the sound of the guns.
سيروا نحو صوت النيران.
In science, the exact opposite is the case: March away from the sound of the guns.
لكن الحالة في العلوم هي العكس تماما: سيروا بعيدا عن صوت النيران.
So Wilson's Principle Number Three:
لذلك, مبدأ وبيلسون الثالث:
March away from the sound of the guns.
سر بعيدا عن صوت النيران.
Observe from a distance,
وراقب من بعيد،
but do not join the fray.
لكن لا تنضم الى المعركة.
Make a fray of your own.
إصنع معركتك الخاصة.
Once you have settled on a specialty,
عندما تستقر على تخصص معين،
and the profession you can love, and you've secured opportunity,
و المجال الذي يمكنك أن تحبه، و تؤمن فرصتك فيه،
your potential to succeed will be greatly enhanced if you study it
فإن فرصتك في النجاح ستعلو كثيرا إذا درست هذا المجال
enough to become an expert.
بما فيه الكفاية لتحترفه.
There are thousands of professionally delimited
يوجد الآلاف من المواضيع المحددة مهنيا
subjects sprinkled through physics and chemistry
موزعة من الفيزياء والكيمياء
to biology and medicine.
إلى الأحياء والطب.
And on then into the social sciences,
والعلوم الإنسانية،
where it is possible in short time to acquire
حيث يمكن الحصول فيها في وقت وجيز
the status of an authority.
على وضعية سلطة معرفية.
When the subject is still very thinly populated,
عندما يكون عدد المهتمين بالموضوع قليل،
you can with diligence and hard work become
يمكنك عن طريق الاجتهاد والعمل الجاد أن تصبح
the world authority.
السلطة المعرفية العالمية.
The world needs this kind of expertise,
والعالم يحتاج إلى هذا النوع من الخبرات،
and it rewards the kind of people
و يكافئ النوع من الناس
willing to acquire it.
الذين يريدون اكتسابه.
The existing information and what you self-discover
إن المعلومات الموجودة مسبقا و ما تكتشفه بنفسك
may at first seem skimpy and difficult to connect
قد يكون للوهلة الأول غريبا وصعبا للربط
to other bodies of knowledge.
مع بقية المعارف.
Well, if that's the case,
حسنا، إذا كانت هذه هي القضية،
good. Why hard instead of easy?
فهذا جيد. لماذا صعب بدلا من سهل؟
The answer deserves to be stated as Principle Number Four.
تستحق الإجابة أن تدرج كمبدأ رابع.
In the attempt to make scientific discoveries,
في محاولة لإيجاد إكتشافات علمية،
every problem is an opportunity,
كل مشكلة هي فرصة،
and the more difficult the problem,
وبقدر صعوبة المشكلة،
the greater will be the importance of its solution.
بقدر أهمية حلها.
Now this brings me to a basic categorization
وهذا يقودني إلى تصنيف أساسي
in the way scientific discoveries are made.
لكيفية تحقيق الاكتشافات العلمية.
Scientists, pure mathematicians among them,
العلماء وضمنهم علماء الرياضيات البحتة،
follow one or the other of two pathways:
يتبعون أحد مسارين:
First through early discoveries,
أولا، من خلال الإكتشافات المبكرة،
a problem is identified
يتم تحديد المشكل
and a solution is sought.
والبحث عن حل.
The problem may be relatively small;
والمشكلة هي صغيرة نسبيا؛
for example, where exactly in a cruise ship does the norovirus begin to spread?
على سبيل المثال، أين بالتحديد على السفينة يبدأ النوروفيروس بالانتشار؟
Or larger, what's the role of dark matter in the expansion of the universe?
أو ما دور المادة السوداء في اتساع الكون؟
As the answer is sought, other phenomena are typically discovered
في سياق البحث عن إجابة، بعض الظواهر تكتشف بالعادة
and other questions are asked.
و أسئلة أخرى تطرح.
This first of the two strategies is like a hunter,
الإستراتيجية الأولى من الإثنتين هي كقناص،
exploring a forest in search of a particular quarry,
يكتشف الغابة بحثا عن طريدة معينة،
who finds other quarries along the way.
ولكنه يرى طرائد أخرى في طريقه.
The second strategy of research
و الإستراتيجية الثانية للبحث
is to study a subject broadly
هي عن طريق دراسة الموضوع بشكل موسع
searching for unknown phenomena or patterns of known phenomena
بحثاَ عن ظواهر غير معروفة أو أنماط لظاهرة معروفة
like a hunter in what we call "the naturalist's trance,"
مثل قناص فيما نطلق عليه: "نشوة الطبيعي،"
the researcher of mind is open to anything interesting,
الباحث في العقل هو منفتح على أي شيء مثير للإهتمام،
any quarry worth taking.
أي طريدة تستحق الأخذ.
The search is not for the solution of the problem,
إن البحث هو ليس عن حل للمشكلة،
but for problems themselves worth solving.
لكن للمشاكل ذاتها والتي تستحق أن تحل.
The two strategies of research,
إستراتيجيتا البحث،
original research, can be stated as follows,
البحث الأصلي، يمكن أن يصاغ كما يلي،
in the final principle I'm going to offer you:
في المبدأ الأخير الذي سأعرضه عليكم:
For every problem in a given discipline of science,
لكل مشكلة في مجال من العلوم،
there exists a species or entity or phenomenon
يوجد هناك صنف أو كيان أو ظاهرة
ideal for its solution.
مثالية لحلها.
And conversely, for every species or other entity
وبالعكس، لكل صنف أو كيان آخر
or phenomenon, there exist important problems
أو ظاهرة، توجد مشاكل مهمة
for the solution of which, those particular objects of research are ideally suited.
للحل الذي يطابق مجالات البحث تلك تماما.
Find out what they are.
ابحث عنها.
You'll find your own way to discover,
وستجد طريقتك لتكتشف،
to learn, to teach.
ولتتعلم وتُعلّم.
The decades ahead will see dramatic advances
إن العقود من الزمن الآتية ستشهد تقدما دراماتيكيا
in disease prevention, general health, the quality of life.
في الوقاية من الأمراض و الصحة العامة و جودة الحياة.
All of humanity depends on the knowledge and practice of the medicine and the science
كل البشرية تعتمد على المعرفة وممارسة الطب والعلم
behind it you will master.
المعتمدة عليه الذي ستتقنه.
You have chosen a calling that will come in steps
لقد اخترتم نداءً سيأتي على خطوات
to give you satisfaction, at its conclusion, of a life well lived.
ليعطيكم الرضى في خلاصته، لحياة عشتموها جيدا.
And I thank you for having me here tonight.
وأشكركم على استضافتي هنا الليلة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Oh, thank you.
أوه، شكرا لكم.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
I salute you.
تحياتي لكم.